<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief vindication of free grace ... relating to several positions asserted by M. John Goodwin in his late book entituled, Redemption redeem'd, and in his former treatise of justification : delivered in a sermon before the Right Honourable, the Lord Mayor and aldermen of the city of London, at Pauls, May 30, 1652 / by John Pawson ...</title>
            <author>Pawson, John, 1619 or 20-1654?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56727</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P880</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13411</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12254918</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12254918</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57355</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56727)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57355)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 157:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief vindication of free grace ... relating to several positions asserted by M. John Goodwin in his late book entituled, Redemption redeem'd, and in his former treatise of justification : delivered in a sermon before the Right Honourable, the Lord Mayor and aldermen of the city of London, at Pauls, May 30, 1652 / by John Pawson ...</title>
                  <author>Pawson, John, 1619 or 20-1654?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Peter Cole, and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Goodwin, John, 1594?-1665. --  Redemption redeemed.</term>
               <term>Grace (Theology) --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57355:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57355:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Brief VINDICATION OF Free Grace.</p>
            <p>Indeavouring to prove,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That we are not elected as holy but that we ſhould be holy; and that Election is not of kindes, but perſons.</item>
               <item>2. That Chriſt did not by his death intend to ſave all men, and touching thoſe whom he intended to ſave, that he did not dy for them only if they would believe, but that they might believe.</item>
               <item>3. That we are not juſtified properly by our believing in Chriſt, but by our Christ believed in.</item>
               <item>4. That that which differences one man from another, is not the improvement of a common ability reſtored through Chriſt to all men in general, but a principle of grace wrought by the Spirit of God in the Elect.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Relating to ſeveral Poſitions aſſerted by M. <hi>John Goodwin</hi> in his late Book entituled <hi>Redemption Redeem</hi>'d, and in his former Treatiſe of <hi>Juſtification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Delivered in a Sermon before the Right Honourable, the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of the City of <hi>London,</hi> at <hi>Pauls, May</hi> 30. 1652.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> John Pawſon <hi>late Follow of S.</hi> John's <hi>Colledge in</hi> Cambridge, <hi>and now Miniſter of the Goſpel at</hi> Hemmingford Abbots <hi>in Huntingdon ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>1 COR. 15. 10.</bibl>
            <q>By the grace of God I am what I am.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Peter Cole</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the ſigne of the <hi>Printing Preſs in Cornhill,</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:57355:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Kendrick</hi> Mayor,</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Tueſday the 15. day of June, 1652.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is thought fit, and ſo Ordered by this Court, that M. <hi>John Pawſon</hi> be deſired to Print his Sermon preached at <hi>Pauls,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord Mayor and Aldermen, on the thirtieth day of <hi>May</hi> laſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sadler.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:57355:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Honourable,</hi> John Kendricke <hi>Lord Mayor;</hi> His Honoured Uncle, <hi>THOMAS ATKIN;</hi> His honoured Friends, <hi>John Dethicke,</hi> and <hi>Robert Tychburne,</hi> Aldermen of the City of <hi>London;</hi> With the reſt of the Court of Aldermen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Intent in the enſuing Diſcourſe, is, to contribute my Mite towards the vindicating of Free Grace; in the <hi>Dedication</hi> to teſtifie my thankfulneſs to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of you, for real courteſies; to you all, for ample expreſſions of undeſerved respect towards me. In both which I indeavour brevity; eſteeming many words but cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſome, when the mind may be delivered and received in few. The ſum of what I lately preached before you, and now again at your call, here preſent to you, appears in the Title page: which things I have breifly contended for; as conceiving them truths, once and again delivered to the Saints, &amp; own'd through ſucceſſive generations by the choyceſt of Saints. The ſubſtance aad ſtrength of what <hi>Arminius</hi> &amp; others with him, have heretofore pleaded for the contary is now Engliſhed, by the Reverend Author of <hi>Redemption
<pb facs="tcp:57355:3"/> Redeem'd:</hi> And therefore I have all along related to ſome ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial paſſages of his book without the leaſt diſhonourable reflection upon his perſon, whom I really honour for piety, parts, and painful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (during many years paſt) in the work of the Lord. Though we cannot meet in the acknowledgment of theſe points, yet I hope to meet him in the boſome of Chriſt. In the mean time it concerns you, and us all, who make mention of the Lord, to pray out the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of thoſe promiſes which God hath made to theſe latter ages; one whereof is this, that <hi>he will turn to his people a pure language; Zeph. 3. 9.</hi> they ſhall not ſpeak a mixed language, one, one way; and another quite contrary, but ſhall all ſerve the Lord with one conſent.</p>
            <p>Till that fulneſs of time come, there will be great <hi>running to and fro</hi> in the * Prophet's ſenſe, <hi>i e.</hi> great debating things to and<note place="margin">Dan. 12. 4.</note> fro, even amongſt the Saints: which yet in this regard will be an advantage, that hereby <hi>knowledge ſhall be increaſed.</hi> Every con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable debate will either further draw out, or cleare up ſome truth or other. So that though the many and hot diſputes of this age, be in ſome reſpects trouble ſome to the people of God at preſent yet the Remnant of Iſrael in after time will inherit the benefit of them.</p>
            <p>May your City be not only as old <hi>Tyre</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> whoſe Merchants were Princes and Traffiquers, the Honorable of the earth; but as the new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> a holy City, a City of righteouſneſs, a faithfull city; the Citizens, Saints, and each family a houſehold of God. So prays</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant in Chriſt Jeſus John Pawſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57355:3"/>
            <head>A Brief VINDICATION OF Free Grace.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>EPHES. 2. 5.</bibl>
               <q>By Grace ye are ſaved.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od's great deſign in ſetting up the World, and diſpoſing of the things in it, was, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt himſelf in all his Attributes. In ſome things God is ſaid to have manifeſted his wiſdom, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 104. 24. <hi>O Lord how mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold are thy Works? In Wiſdom haſt thou made them all.</hi> In ſome things God had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the manifeſting of his Might and Soveraignty; in ſeverall Texts <hi>this</hi> and <hi>that</hi> (ſayes God) <hi>I will do and you ſhall know that I am the Lord.</hi> Now as God hath made proviſion in his ſeveral Diſpenſations, to manifeſt all his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Attributes one way or other; ſo he hath contrived to carry on the work of our Salvation, in ſuch a way, as might manifeſt his Mercy and Grace in a ſpecial manner.</p>
            <p>And therefore it concerns us, to be careful in all our thoughts and diſcourſes, to advance and keep up <hi>free Grace.</hi> We ſhould not, nor need not throw down any other Attribute, to advance this; but yet we may ſafely in ſome ſenſe advance this above any other, 'Tis an Attribute God himſelf ſeems to take exceeding pleaſure in manifeſting. He is ſaid to <hi>delight in ſhewing Mercy, or Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſide 'tis an Attribute that we are more beholding to, then any other Attribute whatever. The Wiſdom and Power of God have a great hand in making of us; but the <hi>Grace</hi> of God hath the greateſt hand in ſaving of us: <hi>By his Grace ye are ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:57355:4"/>
            <p>Obſerv. <hi>The whole buſineſs of our Salvation, is carried on in a way of free Grace, from firſt to laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This God hath contriv'd on purpoſe, that he might exclude Boaſting; <hi>that no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence;</hi> but that <hi>he who Gloryeth ſhould Glory in the Lord;</hi> and ſay, <hi>what have I that I have not received.</hi> Heaven it ſelf is a Donative; and every ſtep in the Ladder to Heaven, is <hi>free Grace;</hi> every Stone of our ſpiritual building every Beam of our day, every Link in our chain of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is <hi>free grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are four main links Election Redemption Juſtification and Regeneration which I name the laſt, becauſe the proper work of the Spirit: I ſhall indeavour to ſhew, that each of theſe is made out of <hi>free Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. Election is made out of <hi>free grace, Rom.</hi> 11. 5. we read <hi>of the election of grace. i. e.</hi> ſuch an election as grace makes, an election of grace's making; as <hi>Beza</hi> expounds it. Grace elects and picks out this and that perſon.<note n="*" place="margin">M. I. <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win</hi> Red. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, pag. 63.</note> Election is of perſons, not of kinds; of individuals, not of <hi>Species's.</hi> God elected ſuch and ſuch perſons in particular; not perſons ſo and ſo qualified in general: he elected <hi>Peter,</hi> as <hi>Peter;</hi> not <hi>Peter,</hi> as a Believer, or as a righteous perſon; for ſuch an election would not have been an election of <hi>grace,</hi> but an election of <hi>juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 4. We are ſaid to be <hi>choſen before the foundation of the world:</hi> Therefore God does not ſtay to ſee what we will prove before he chuſe us. If he choſe us ſo ſoon, his election ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther makes us holy, then finds us holy: and this is clear from the next words; <hi>He hath choſen us before the foundation of the world, that we ſhould be holy.</hi> If he choſe us, that we ſhould be holy; then he did not chuſe us as holy. There is no ſuch phraſe in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, that God elected us as believers, or in caſe we believe; and therefore to ſay that * election is only the ſtanding good pleaſure<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem page</hi> 62.</note> and purpoſe of God, to give life to all thoſe that believe, is <hi>gratis dictum;</hi> nor is it true: for though there be ſuch a purpoſe in God, yet this is not that purpoſe which the Scripture calls election. Election always carries ſalvation along with it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 30. <hi>Whom he predeſtinated</hi> (and conſequently whom he elected) <hi>them be alſo calleth, and juſtifieth, and will glorify:</hi> But now, notwithſtanding ſuch a purpoſe to ſave whoever believes all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57355:4"/> might periſh; therefore ſuch a purpoſe is not that which Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture means by predeſtination and election; for ſuch a purpoſe might ſtand, and yet God have no people, Chriſt be a head with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a body, a King without Subjects.</p>
            <p>Some affirme that * election is not an act of God, that is paſs'd;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> page 62.</note> but that when God prevails by his word and ſpirit with men in time to believe; then he is ſaid to have erected them.</p>
            <p>But this is flat contrary to the Apoſtle, for <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 4. the Saints at <hi>Epheſus</hi> were elected <hi>before the foundation of the world;</hi> and yet <hi>ver.</hi> 13. they believed not, till after they heard the word of truth. This ſeems to overthrow what ſome build upon as a foundation, <hi>viz.</hi> that * no act of God is before any act of the Creature, in<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> p. 53.</note> reſpect of time. If by time be meant duration (as ſurely muſt) that ſaying is void of truth, for the act of God electing, was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the foundation of the world; and the act of the Epheſians believing, was not till after they heard the word of truth: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one apparently before the other, in reſpect of duration.</p>
            <p>Whereas 'tis ſaid, that * God acteth but once for all; and that<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> p. 58.</note> * God by one act produceth all things; tis true, in ſome ſenſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> p. 60.</note> that God by one act does all things: but yet if we will ſpeak af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of men, and ſo as to be underſtood, we muſt ſay, that this one act in God, is diverſifyed, and multiplyed in the creature, according to the objects upon which 'tis terminated. Who knows not but that in ſome ſenſe, whatever God did here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, does now, or will do hereafter, is but one continued act as in God, becauſe 'tis himſelf, who is but one, and done in eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which is <hi>duratio tota ſimul.</hi> But yet though it be but one ſingle act <hi>quoad eſſe;</hi> notwithſtanding, 'tis diverſifyed and multiplyed, <hi>quoad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erminar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> though all the acts of God, are the ſame as ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectively in God; yet as they are objectively put forth upon the Creatures, ſo they are different; and one before another. We cannot truly ſay, that God created the world, and burn'd down <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> both at once; they were different acts, as from God, and one done before the other. 'Tis clear enough that ſome of God's acts are before others; and much clearer that ſome acts of God are before ſome acts of the creature. Did not God make <hi>Adam,</hi> before that <hi>Cain</hi> whom <hi>Adam</hi> begot ſlew his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? To ſay that no act of God is before any act of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57355:5"/> is new Metaphyſicks; and thereupon to ſay, that God's electing is not before our believing is new divinity; both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Apoſtle, who ſays, that the Saints, at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> were choſen <hi>before the foundation of the world;</hi> and yet believed not, till <hi>after</hi> they heard the word of truth.</p>
            <p>Gods grace and love was on worke in electing <hi>Peter,</hi> before either <hi>Peter</hi> or the world was: * nor does it follow, that when<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> p. 63.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> came into the world, and liv'd in a ſinfull eſtate before his converſion, that then God muſt have chang'd his affection, and take off his love from him till after his converſion; for God lov'd <hi>Peter</hi> before his converſion, even while he was in a ſinful eſtate; though not with a love of well-likeing in him, yet with a love of wellwilling to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter</hi> after his converſion lov'd God, but God lov'd <hi>Peter,</hi> before <hi>Peter</hi> lov'd him; 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. 19. <hi>We love him, becauſe he firſt loved us.</hi> God loves us firſt, he begins to us in point of love, therefore he loves us before our converſion, for after our conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion we love him.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the ſcripture ſays, <hi>God hates all workers of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> and ſuch are all elect perſons before converſion: but yet, though he hate them as workers of iniquity, <hi>i. e.</hi> takes no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in them; yet he loves them as elect perſons: <hi>i. e.</hi> beares a good will to them. Nor is it any contradiction in this ſenſe for the ſame perſon to love and hate the ſame man, at the ſame time, upon a ſeveral accompt, as a father may hate a ſon, as he is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly and undutifull, and yet at the ſame time bear a good will to him, as he is his own fleſh and blood, and one who he hopes may be reclaimed hereafter: even ſo may God hate an elect perſon, as he is a worker of iniquity before converſion, and yet at the ſame time bear a love of good-will to him, as he is a choſen veſſel, and one who he knows will be converted and come in hereafter. In <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13. 18. God is ſaid to have <hi>poured out his fury upon the Iſraelites;</hi> this was an argument of hatred: and yet while he was doing ſo, he is ſaid to have <hi>pittyed them, ver.</hi> 21. and this was an argument that he bare love and good will to them; as they ſhed blood in the land; and poluted it with Idols, ſo he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, and powred out his fury upon them, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. but yet Iſrael was his own peculiar people; and upon that account he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57355:5"/> bare ſuch good will to them, as that he promiſes, <hi>ver.</hi> 25, 26. to <hi>cleuſe them from their filthineſs, and from their Idols, and to give them new hearts, and new Spirits.</hi> Which argues, that though at preſent he took no likeing nor pleaſure in them, yet even then he bare good-will, and intended good to them. God may bear love, and intend good to thoſe whom at preſent he hates as workers of iniquity; and thus it is in the caſe of every elect perſon before converſion.</p>
            <p>God loves us before our converſion, yea before the foundation of the world; for he elected us ſo ſoon; and therefore God's love electing, does not ſtay for our believing; free grace was up and at work more early then ſo.</p>
            <p>The decree of election is no impediment, and therefore ſhould<note place="margin">Appl. 1.</note> be no diſcouragement to any. No decree of God cauſes any to ſin, nor will damn any that repent and believe: whoever periſh, tis becauſe of their not-believing, not becauſe of God's not-electing; and therefore to reaſon thus, God's decree muſt be fulfilled upon me, therefore no matter what I do, nor how I live; it argues both a wicked heart, and a weak head: it argues a wicked heart, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>when men once begin ſo to reaſon, 'tis a ſigne they are reſolv'd to ſit down in their wicked ways, and to run a hazard for ſalvation; and then it argues a weak head, for as 'tis an argument of wiſdom to uſe fit meanes for obtayning an appointed end, ſo 'tis an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of weaknes, from the appointment of the end, to infer a neglect of means: 'tis as if <hi>Hezekiah</hi> after notice of God's pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to prolong his life 15. years, ſhould thereupon have deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined neither to eat nor drink thenceforward. A decree about the end does not exclude but include the uſe of means: though God had decreed to ſave all thoſe that were in the ſhip with <hi>Paul,</hi> and had revealed ſo much to <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 27. 24. yet the Apoſtle crys out, <hi>ver.</hi> 31. <hi>except the Mariners abide in the ſhip, ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaved;</hi> notwithſtanding the decree of election, <hi>without faith and holineſs, no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi> Let none preſume they can be ſaved by election, without a cloſeing with Jeſus Chriſt; and let none doubt but they are elected, if they feel that they cloſe with Jeſus Chriſt upon Goſpel-terms; this is making our election ſure: a true ſenſe and feeling<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that we rely firmely upon Chriſt, and indeavour unfeignedly to be conformable to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57355:6"/> Chriſt, is a good aſſurance of our election: if we can find the law of God writ powerfully in our hearts, we may be aſſured our names are writ infallibly in the booke of life.</p>
            <p>The decree of election as it is no diſcouragement to any ſo 'tis<note place="margin">
                  <hi>App.</hi> 2.</note> an exceeding incouragement to believers, when they labour and groan under the preſſures of the world the weakneſſes of the fleſh, the out-breakings of corruption, the in-breakings of Satan; what an incouragement is this to conſider, that their ſalvation is not founded upon their own changeable wills, but upon the will of God, which is unchangeable? All our own foundations would have been unſure, but the foundation of the Lord is ſure; and this is that foundation.</p>
            <p>Let Conſcience, Law, Sin, Hell, and Devils, bring in all their ſtrength, <hi>we are more then Conquerours,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 8. 37. why what's the reaſon? This is one reaſon, <hi>who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of God's elect? ver.</hi> 33. election is one ground of confidence and incouragement, to a believer that hath made his election ſure.</p>
            <p>2. I proceed to the next link in the Chain of our Salvation, which is Redemption. And this likewiſe is made out of <hi>free Grace.</hi> Eph. 1. 7. <hi>in whom we have redemption through his Blood, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the riches of his Grace.</hi> Mark how the Apoſtle in this <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. paſſes from one link of the Chain to the other; from Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination and Election, to Redemption; faſtning both the links upon the ſame perſons. Whom the Father before the Foundation of the World Elected, <hi>to the praiſe of the Glory of his Grace,</hi> ver. 6. thoſe the Son in the fulnes of time Redeemed, <hi>according to the riches of his grace,</hi> ver. 7. whom the Father out of <hi>free Grace</hi> elected, he gave them to the Son; and the Son out of <hi>free Grace</hi> redeems them, and gives eternal Life to them.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſaid <hi>John</hi> 17. 2. that <hi>the Son was to give Eternal Life to as many as the Father gave him:</hi> To as many, therefore not to any more. Some the Father did not give to Chriſt in the ſenſe ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of; for Joh. 6. 39. Chriſt tells us, <hi>that of all which the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath given him, he would loſe nothing, but raiſe it up at the laſt Day: i. e.</hi> to eternal Life as the next verſe explaines it. Chriſt loſes none that the Father gave him, and therefore they who everlaſtingly miſcarry, the Father never gave them to Chriſt, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57355:6"/> conſequently Chriſt never gave himſelf for them. That place <hi>John</hi> 17. 12. does not prove that the Son of predition was one of thoſe the Father gave to Chriſt, but rather the contrary: for the ſenſe may, and (compared with <hi>John</hi> 6. 37, 39.) muſt run thus, <hi>viz. Thoſe that thou gaveſt me I have kept, and none of them is loſt: but the Son of perdition is loſt: i. e.</hi> As he is none of thoſe that thou gaveſt me; the term [<hi>but</hi>] being here taken, not by way of exception, but by way of oppoſition; as it is elſe where in Scripture: <hi>Luke</hi> 4. 26, 27. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 16. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 27. and as we frequently uſe it in common diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Nor will that Text, <hi>John</hi> 17. 2. indure to be reſtrained to * the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> p. 118.</note> Apoſtles only; where Chriſt is ſaid, <hi>to give eternal Life to as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as the Father gave him:</hi> for the term [as many <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>quotquot</hi>] is too comprehenſive and large to be reſtrained to ſo few as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; eſpecially conſidering 'tis put as a ſutable ſubſumption under that general term [<hi>all fleſh</hi> immediately foregoing; it would make the lenſe run thus, <hi>thou haſt given him power over all fleſh, that he might give Eternal Life to a few Apostles;</hi> which ſeems not a little incongruous. Indeed at <hi>ver.</hi> 6. Chriſt begins to ſpeak more particularly of the Apoſtles, and ſo goes on for ſome verſes; But at <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. he inlarges his diſcourſe, and apparently ſpeaks of all Believers; and at <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. ſtill ſpeaking of all that ever ſhall beleive, he uſes the ſame form of ſpeech as he did before in <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Father, I will, that they whom thou haſt given me, be with me, where I am, that they may be hold my Glory:</hi> this word <hi>Glory,</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe explains what is meant by eternal life, in <hi>ver. 2. i. e.</hi> * not<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> p. 117.</note> means of Grace only, but Glory it ſelf, with Chriſt in Heaven. <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I will,</hi> ſays Chriſt; he ſpeaks not only by way of intreaty but as it were, by way of demand. He had ſaid before, <hi>Father, I have finiſhed thy work:</hi> and as one that had done his work, now he comes to demand his wages; what's that? <hi>Father, I will that they whom thou haſt given me, may partake of my glory:</hi> who are they? they are the ſame whom <hi>ver.</hi> 23. <hi>the Father hath loved, as he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Chriſt:</hi> How is that? he loved Chriſt <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. <hi>before the foundation of the World.</hi> From whence this will cleerly follow, God did not love onely the Apoſtles before the foundation of the World; therefore they were not the only perſons whom the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gave unto Chriſt. Neither did he love all men, as he loved
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57355:7"/> Chriſt, before the foundation of the World; he did not love <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> ſo; therefore they were not of thoſe whom the Father gave to Chriſt, and conſequently he did not give all. But whom the Father choſe before the foundation of the World, 'tis a ſure argument, that thoſe he lov'd before the foundation of the World, and thoſe he gave to Chriſt; for thoſe Chriſt undertook the work of Redemption; and having finiſhed the worke, for thoſe he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands Heaven, and Glory, as having Redeemed them from Hell and Miſery.</p>
            <p>No doubt but there was worth enough in Chriſt's death and merits, to have redeemed as many worlds of men, as there be men in the world; but the intent of Chriſt in the work of Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, was to purſue the deſign of God in election. And this (no other) is the meaning of that diſtinction betwixt the ſufficiency of Chriſt's death, and the intention of it. We do not ſay, that Chriſt dyed intentionally for the elect only; and yet dyed ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for all: and therefore all the * arguments muſtered up againſt the diſtirction in that ſenſe, do but ſtrike at a ſhadow, and beat the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> p. 94. 95. &amp;c.</note> Ayr. But we ſay, it being impoſſible Chriſt ſhould have a deſign beyond and diſtinct from his Father; therefore he intended to redeeme his Fathers elect only; though otherwiſe, there was in the price he paid, a ſufficiency to have redeemed all. We do not diſtinguiſh betwixt Chriſt dying ſufficiently and intentionally, but betwixt the ſufficiency of Chriſt's death, and the intention of Chriſt dying. Chriſts death was ſufficient to have redeemed thoſe whom he never bare any love to; but whom Chriſt intended to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem and ſave, and to that very end laid down his life for them, thoſe he did love; yea he could not poſſibly bear more love, nor intend a greater good to any, then that amounts to; <hi>Greater love hath no man then this, to lay down his life for another.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if Chriſt lay'd down his life for all and every one, even for <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> with an intent to ſave them; then he did bear no more love, nor intend no more good to <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> then he did to them; no more grace to one, then to another. This does exceedingly derogate from the worth of <hi>free grace,</hi> and makes it no ſuch peculiar choice thing, as the Scripture ſets it ſorth. For the vindication of <hi>free grace</hi> in this point, I ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> two arguments, to prove, that the intent of Chriſt in
<pb facs="tcp:57355:7"/> dying was to purſue the deſigne of God, in electing, and not to redeem all.</p>
            <p>1. Whom Chriſt intended to Redeem, he laid down his life to make a purchaſe for them; and Faith was one part of the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, one of thoſe things which he purchaſed for them; <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 29. <hi>Unto you it is given, in the behalf of Chriſt, to believe,</hi> &amp;c. In the Original it is, <hi>To you it is given to believe,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>for Chriſt's ſake,</hi> upon his account, as purchaſed by him. So that Faith is part of what Chriſt purchaſed by his death: But Chriſt hath not purchaſed faith for all, therefore he did not lay down his life for all.</p>
            <p>Whom Chriſt intended to ſave by his death he did not dye for them only if they would believe, but that they might believe. Whoever believes, <hi>Its given to them to believe,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>for Chriſts ſake,</hi> as an effect of his merits. God intended that none ſhould have ſalvation without this condition of believing: Chriſt intended by his death and merits, to purchaſe both ſalvation for the Elect and this condition alſo in order thereunto.</p>
            <p>2. If God and Chriſt intended all ſhould be redeemed and ſaved, then all would certainly have been ſaved: For whatever any Underſtanding Agent intends to effect, he alwaies effects it; unleſs he either find the thing firſt intended, to prove afterwards inconvenient, or elſe want power to bring to effect what be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, Now God being infinite in Wiſdom to foreſee all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceniences, and infinite in power to effect what he ſees con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, it is impoſſible that ever he ſhould intend to effect any thing, and that thing not be effected. And therefore to maintain that * God may be ſaid to intend to effect what never is effected, is<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> p. 33.</note> a new Notion, where Reaſon and Truth are ſo far from greeting one the other in it, that neither of them will come neer it.</p>
            <p>Nor is there any ground either in Scripture or Reaſon, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt Gods intentions or purpoſes and his decrees. To ſay that * God does not alwaies decree the effecting of what he<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> p. 36.</note> purpoſes, is <hi>gratis dictum;</hi> and to ſay, that * though what God<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> Decrees doth alwaies ſtand, yet what he purpoſes, doth ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times not ſtand, is expreſly contrary to that Text, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14. 24. <hi>As I have purpoſed, it ſhall ſtand.</hi> Gods purpoſe is eternal, and what he works in time, he works according to that eternal pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. 11. therefore his purpoſes change not, and what he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57355:8"/> purpoſes muſt ſtand. The Purpoſes or Decrees of God are the foundation of all his workings; and <hi>the foundation of God ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſure:</hi> Therefore if God and Chriſt had purpoſed and intended to ſave all, then all had ſurely been ſaved.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe Texts which are alledged to prove that Chriſt Redeemed the World, or all men in it, they are indeed many and I cannot there inſiſt upon them particularly, only thus much to them in general.</p>
            <p>They prove that all men in the world who are redeemed and ſaved, are redeemed and ſaved by Chriſt; his merits the only ranſome for all, and he the only Saviour of all who are ſav'd in the world: But that he intended to redeem and ſave every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular man in the world, not any, nor all of thoſe Texts together, ſpeak home to the proof of it; and till that be proved, <hi>Univerſal Redemption</hi> is not <hi>Redeemed,</hi> but muſt unavoydably periſh not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the language and wit that is laid down and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed for the ſaving of it.</p>
            <p>Towards the clearing thoſe places, where the World and all men are ſaid to be redeemed theſe four things may be conſiderable.</p>
            <p>1. The Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 12, 15. by the world, means the Gentiles, as a people to whom Chriſt was to be a Meſſiah, as well as to the Jews; Therefore to ſay that the world may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the Gentiles is not a ſpeech to be hooted at, for the Scripture will avouch ſuch a ſenſe of the VVord.</p>
            <p>2. The Texts alledged will bear ſuch a ſenſe, <hi>viz.</hi> That though formerly the Covenant of Grace was reſtrained only to the Jews, and all the Gentiles (the reſt of the world) excluded; yet now God would have a people even among the Gentiles, throughout the wide world, redeemed by Chriſt out of all Nations and Languages.</p>
            <p>3. Such a ſenſe is agreeable to the analogie of other Scriptures, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 9. <hi>Thou haſt redeemed us by thy blood, out of every kinred, Tongue and People and Nation.</hi> This Text lifts up its voice aloud againſt Univerſal Redemption; For if Chriſt hath redeemed out of every Kinred Tongue, People, and Nation; then he hahnot redeemed every Kinred; People and Nation. Pertinent hereunto, is that Prophecy of <hi>Caiaphas, Joh.</hi> 11. 51, 52. who though a wicked man yet he ſpake not of himſelf, but as high Prieſt that yeer: which implies that his tongue was guided from above, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57355:8"/> that he ſpake a Truth, prophecying that Jeſus ſhould dy for that Nation of the Jews, and not for that Nation only, but that alſo he ſhould gather together in one, the children of God that were ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered abroad. Which compared with the former place, imports thus much, That Chriſt dyed not only for the Nation of the Jews, but for all other Nations: Yet how? Not for all particular perſons, but for the children of God, both in that Nation of the Jews, and ſcattered abroad elſe-where, throughout the world in any other Nation. Even as under the Law the Jews were God's only Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant people, <hi>i. e:</hi> not every particular perſon of the Jews was ſpiritually in Covenant with God but the faithful elect of that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: So now, not only the Jews, but all Nations, all the world have title to Chriſts death, <hi>i. e.</hi> not all Individual perſons but the Elect in all Nations throughout the wide world.</p>
            <p>4. The Jews generally run upon this miſtake, that the Meſſiah and ſalvation, by him belonged only to themſelves 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 15. 16. <hi>They are contrary to all men</hi> (where by the way mark that all men is taken in oppoſition to the Jews) <hi>ſo bidding us to ſpeak to the Gentiles, that they might be ſaved.</hi> They made accompt ſalvation by Chriſt concerned only themſelves not the Gentiles; yea the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples and Followers of Chriſt were for a time doubtful at leaſt, as to this caſe, ſuppoſing (it may be) from that Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 6. that they were to preach Chriſt <hi>only to the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael:</hi> For if you compare <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 1. with <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 19. you ſhall find, that they which were ſcattered abroad upon the perſecution that aroſe about <hi>Stephen</hi> though they travell'd far, yet ſtill they preached the word to none, but unto the Jews only: and in <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 45. when the Believing Jews heard that the ſpirit was poured out alſo upon the Gentiles it's ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>they were aſtoniſhed.</hi> So <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 1, 2. <hi>When ſome of the Apoſtles and Brethren, heard that the Gentiles received the word, through</hi> Peters <hi>miniſtry; they contended with</hi> Peter for medling with them; till <hi>Peter</hi> gave an accompt of it, and then at <hi>ver.</hi> 18. <hi>they glorified God; ſaying, then hath God alſo to the Gentiles granted repentance unto life;</hi> wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at it, as a thing which before they did not it ſeems) underſtand.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing not only the Jews generally but even ſome of the Apoſtles and Diſciples of Chriſt, were for a time in this miſtake; 'tis no marvel that the new Teſtament is ſo abundant in general
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57355:9"/> expreſſions, importing that Chriſts death, and the promiſes, did not only belong to the Jews; but to the wide world of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and to <hi>all</hi> men: meaning by <hi>all,</hi> not all particulars, but all kinds; as the word is undeniably uſed, <hi>Luk</hi> 11. 42. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 23. and as that place of renown does neceſſarily evince, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 9.</p>
            <p>Though Chriſt did not dy with an intent to ſave all yet mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel have ſufficient ground to preach the Goſpel unto all. The death and merits of Chriſt were of that infinite<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Appl.</hi> 1.</note> worth, that they might have been a price for all, but that they became a price for any, is to be attributed to the intention of God and Chriſt: not the worth of the thing offered, but the intent of the offerer and accepter, is that which gives it the formality of a price. <hi>Gen.</hi> 33. 19. <hi>Jacob bought a parcel of ground of the children of Hamor for an hundred pieces of mony;</hi> whether the ground was juſt in value anſwerable to the 100 pieces, is not ſo conſiderable; 'tis poſſible the 100 pieces might have ſufficed to purchaſe a thing of more worth; but that which made the 100 pieces formally a price for that particular parcel of ground, was, becauſe <hi>Jacob</hi> paid them, and the children of <hi>Hamor</hi> accepted them for that very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and purpoſe: So likewiſe in this caſe, that the death of Chriſt became formally a price, whether for all or ſome, does not ariſe from its own worth, but from the intention of Chriſt offering, and God accepting it for that purpoſe. Now this intention of God and Chriſt being unknown; who thoſe particular elect perſons are, for whom Chriſts death was intended as a price, and yet his death being of it ſelf ſufficient to purchaſe all, hereupon there is ground for the Goſpel to be preached to all, and that we may and ought to call upon all to believe. For when we call upon men to believe, we do not call upon them to believe that Chriſt dyed for them, but to believe in Chriſt, and to <hi>believe there is no name under heaven whereby they can be ſaved, but only Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and that there is enough in Chriſt to ſave all that believe in him: leaving the ſecret counſell and intent of God and Chriſt, as a thing not diſcovered to us, till it appear by the effect.</p>
            <p>That Chriſt intended by his death to ſave only the elect of God<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Appl.</hi> 2.</note> is no little comfort to thoſe that have already made their election ſure; and no manner of diſcomfort to any. For believers to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that they have another kind of intereſt in Chriſt then thoſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57355:9"/> that periſh, is matter of great Conſolation, <hi>Christ loved me, and gave himſelf for me;</hi> This <hi>Paul</hi> tryumphed in, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20. Nor is this juſt matter of diſcomfort to any, as long as this is held forth to every one, <hi>Believe in Chriſt, and you ſhall be ſaved.</hi> He that will find comfort in any Doctrine, muſt ſeek it in the right way, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in according to Gods Word and Will, comfort is to be found. No Doctrine whatever, if true, holds forth comfort to any while they reſolve to continue in a ſinful way. Be careful in walking cloſe with God, and ſeeking him, and you ſhall thereby find, that you are of the number of thoſe that Chriſt died for. Aſſoon as your own hearts aſſure you that you repent and believe, the Scripture aſſures you that Chriſt died for you. All thoſe that walk in faith &amp; holines will find that Chriſt dyed for them. If corrupt reaſon, and diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered affections cavil at this as uncomfortable, we cannot help it; the Doctrine it ſelf is ſweet: and if any complain of bitterneſs in it, let ſuch conſider whether their own Palate be not diſtempered.</p>
            <p>I go on to the third link in the chain of our ſalvation, which is Juſtification; and this likewiſe is out of Free Grace; <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 2, 4. <hi>Being juſtified freely by his Grace,</hi> &amp;c. Juſtified freely, The word in the Original is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without any price, without any valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able conſideration; importing that we are juſtified <hi>gratis,</hi> without any price, without any valuable conſideration on our own part from our ſelves. For the vindicating of Free Grace in point of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I ſhall endeavour to clear this Propoſition.</p>
            <p>That nothing in our ſelves is of any valuable conſideration in point of juſtifying us. The Papiſts ſay our works are; but that is an opinion now dead among us, and therefore let it lye. Others ſay our faith is: What the Papiſts attribute to works, theſe upon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter attribute the like to faith to <hi>To credere.</hi> They expreſs themſelves to this effect, * In the ſame way that God required perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence<note place="margin">M. <hi>1. Goodw.</hi> In putat of Faith. part 1. page 14.</note> in the firſt Covenant he now requires faith inſteed of it in the ſecond Covenant, ſo that as works ſhould have juſtified them before the fall, ſo Faith now. Chriſt in dying (ſay they) * did not<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem ibidem,</hi> part 2. p. 33.</note> bear the curſe of the Law for us but only obtain that God ſhould juſtifie us upon other terms then before, <hi>i. e.</hi> by accepting faith for our righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>In oppoſition hereunto, I ſhall endeavour to prove, that as faith of it ſelf hath no ſuch worth in it, ſo Chriſt hath not purchaſed any
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57355:10"/> ſuch worth for it, that it ſhould be accounted or paſs for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. How harmleſs ſoever this opinion ſeem at firſt view, yet if we thorowly examine it, and the conſequences that attend it, we ſhall find that it does in the iſſue, attribute too much to ſelf, and too little to Chriſt, and that it derogates from Free Grace, and is contrary to the Goſpel way of Juſtification. I deny not but that Faith is a Goſpel condition, without which we cannot be juſtified, yet not an immediate condition, the very performance whereof is our righteouſneſs, but ſuch a remote conditio, as the performance thereof gives us intereſt in the righteouſneſs of Chriſt the Lord our Righteouſneſs. 'Tis not a condition ſo as works were before the Fall; for the performance of works was that wherein righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs before the Fall, was to conſiſt formally; If faith ſucceed works in ſuch a ſenſe as being inſtead of works (as ſome affirm) then the performance of faith does make formally righteous: if ſo then we may plead our faith at Gods Tribunal in the great day, as <hi>Adam</hi> if he had not fallen, might have pleaded his performance of works. But this cannot be, for 1. When we appear before God's judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat, we muſt plead ſuch a righteouſneſs, as will countervail and anſwer God's juſtice: we cannot be juſtified, but by a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs that will anſwer Juſtice, for God is juſt in juſtifying, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 26. therefore ſuch a righteouſneſs muſt be found out, either inherent in us, or imputed to us, as is every way perfect; that ſo God in juſtifying of us for ſuch a righteouſneſs, may appear to be a juſt juſtifier Now the righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed to us, is ſuch a perfect righteouſneſs, as will fully anſwer the juſtice of God. But for our faith, 'tis ſo far from being a perfect righteouſneſs that it is not a perfect faith: That is perfect to which nothing can be added, but our beſt faith ſtands in need of addition and increaſe: The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles pray'd, <hi>Lord increaſe our Faith;</hi> our faith therefore is not perfect, much leſs a perfect righteouſneſs. To ſay it will find ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation in mercy, though not approbation in juſtice, and ſo paſs for righteouſneſs upon that account, is to make Gods mercy ſhut out his Juſtice, whereas Gods great deſigne was, to manifeſt both thoſe attributes in the juſtification of man, not only (though chiefly) his mercy but likewiſe his juſtice. This appears by that fore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 24. <hi>Being juſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Jeſus Chriſt, whom God hath ſet forth or
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57355:10"/> appoynted</hi> &amp;c. That God would admit of any Redemption for us, and that he would likewiſe provide and appoint a Redeemer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was Grace and Mercy manifeſted; But yet you ſhall ſee, he had an Eye likewiſe to the manifeſtation of his Juſtice; for it follows in the next words, <hi>whom he ſet forth to be a propitiation through faith in his blood; to declare his righteouſneſs</hi> or his juſtice, <hi>that he might be just.</hi> This is quite contrary to that paſſage forecited out of the promoters of <hi>To credere. Chriſt in dying</hi> ſay they, <hi>did not bear the curſe of the Law for us</hi> i. e. ſatisfie juſtice in our ſteed, <hi>but only obtain'd that God ſhould ust fie us upon other terms,</hi> 1. e. accept of our faith for righteouſneſs. No (ſays <hi>Paul</hi>) Chriſt did ſatisfie juſtice for us, God appointed him to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a propitiation, which argues ſatisfaction and appeaſment of Juſtice; and God ſo ordered it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for the declaration of his juſtice, that he might be juſt, or that he might appear to be juſt in juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, as <hi>Paroeus</hi> clears that place.</p>
            <p>Should Chriſt only obtain of God to accept of imperfect faith in ſtead of perfect righteouſnes how would there be any manifeſtation of juſtice in it? yea, conſider wel whether there would be any truth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herein if that ſhould paſs for righteouſneſs which is not ſo indeed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>the judgement of God is according to truth;</hi> that which is not righteouſneſs, cannot be judged and eſteemed ſo before God. Indeed there is in ſome ſenſe, a difference betwixt Gods judging according to juſtice, and according to mercy: But Gods judging according to mercy is not judging a perſon perfectly righteous for a righteouſneſs which is imperfect, but for a perfect righteouſneſs, which is not his own: In this judgement there is both truth and mercy. Truth, in that God eſteems us perfectly righteous, for that righteouſneſs which is every way perfect even the righteouſneſs of Chriſt. Mercy in that he eſteems us righteous, for that righteouſneſs, which is not our own only by imputation ours and of his providing for us. When God judges, declares or eſteems us righteous 'tis for ſome righteouſneſs in us, or imputed to us: we cannot be righteous but by a righteouſneſs; faith is not a righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>2. If faith were a righteouſneſs it would be a ſelf righteouſneſs, for faith is mentioned in Scripture as a thing that is our own. <hi>Mer.</hi> 10. 5. <hi>Thy faith,</hi> ſays Chriſt to <hi>Bartimeus. Col.</hi> 1. 4. <hi>I have heard of your faith.</hi> When we believe, it is not God believes in us, though
<pb facs="tcp:57355:11"/> we do it by his ſepcial aſſiſtance: though it be done by grace in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling &amp; aſſiſting &amp; not by ſtrength of Nature, yet it is we that do it, and the act is properly ours; and being ſo, if we were juſtified by it there would be place for our boaſting in it more or leſs: If <hi>To credere</hi> deſerve the name of a righteouſneſs, 'tis apparently our own righteouſneſs; but <hi>Paul</hi> in point of Juſtification, utterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims his own righteouſneſs; <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 9. He deſires <hi>to be found in Chriſt, not having his own righteouſneſs, which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righteouſneſs which is of God by faith.</hi> In which Text the Apoſtle does not diſtinguiſh ſelf-righteouſneſs into two ſorts, diſclaiming only one of them, but he diſtinguiſhes <hi>inter propriam juſticiam &amp; alienam,</hi> diſcaiming utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all ſelf-righteouſneſs, of what ſort ſoever, as a law-righteouſneſs, and laying hold upon anothers righteouſneſs, <hi>i. e.</hi> Chriſts. This ſeems clear from the antitheſis, <hi>that I may be found in Chriſt, not having mine own righteouſneſs;</hi> i. e. in Chriſt's righteouſneſs, not in mine own; <hi>Not having mine own righteouſneſs,</hi> ſayes the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>but that which is through the faith of Christ;</hi> or what if we conſtrue it thus? <hi>Not having mine own righteouſneſs, but that of Chriſts through faith?</hi> the Originall will bear ſuch a conſtruction, though I will not ground upon it. However this is clear from that latter part of the verſe; the righteouſneſs which <hi>Paul</hi> reſted upon is ſuch a righteouſneſs as comes in through faith, and by faith; therefore faith is neither it, nor any part of it. When faith is ſaid to juſtifie, or to be imputed for righteouſneſs, it is not meant faith of it ſelf, but faith in regard of its cruciſied object. That we do not ſpeak this <hi>gratis,</hi> but upon Scripture grounds, we will inſtance in a chapter where the Apoſtle expreſſes himſelf fully and punctually to the very caſe in hand; it is <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. one of the moſt pregnant places which the promoters of <hi>To credere</hi> make uſe of; where indeed <hi>Paul</hi> affirms that we are juſtified by faith, and that faith is imputed for righteouſneſs; But we ſhall find that <hi>Paul</hi> in that very chapter uſes the word faith again and again, for the object of faith; ſo <hi>v.</hi> 23. <hi>before faith came, we were kept under the law,</hi> &amp;c. and again <hi>v.</hi> 25. <hi>after that faith is come, we are no longer under a Schoolma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter:</hi> By the coming of faith, is here undeniably meant the coming of the object, not the act of faith: and ſo twice in that chapter, <hi>v.</hi> 7. 9. they are ſaid to be the <hi>children of Abraham, who are of faith,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57355:11"/> i. e.</hi> they who are of Chriſt by faith. So that we ſee the Apoſtle in this very chapter wherein he ſpeaks of juſtification by faith, uſes the word faith in a relative and metanimical ſenſe, as it imports Chriſt. Now add hereunto that faith in a proper ſenſe <hi>To cred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re,</hi> the very act cannot be imputed for righteouſneſs, cannot juſtifie as the arguments before evince.</p>
            <p>'Tis true faith in a proper ſenſe, is faith in Chriſt and ſo includes Chriſts righteouſneſs as the object of it; but yet we muſt diſtingniſh betwixt the act and the object though the act cannot be without the object: and ſo the adverſaries themſelves do, when they ſay, that <hi>To credere</hi> is imputed and not Chriſts righteouſneſs they do in thoſe very words diſtinguiſh betwixt the act and the object as we do: Only the thing in queſtion betwixt us is whether we be acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted righteous for that act of ours, of which Chriſts righteouſneſs is the object; or for that righteouſneſs of Chriſt upon which our act is terminated or for both taken together. The firſt makes our act the thing for which we are righteous, Chriſt only the object of it, &amp; ſo eſtabliſhes a ſelf-righteouſneſs wholy. The laſt makes us to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted righteous for a righteouſneſs, from two diſtinct ſubjects our ſelves and Chriſt, which cannot be, and beſide it eſtabliſhes a ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs in part which muſt not be. The middle way only attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes all to Chriſt, when we rely for juſtification not upon our own act but upon Chriſts righteouſneſs the object of it.</p>
            <p>To ſhun all ambiguity in terms, we mean in plainer terms thus; There is an apparent difference betwixt believing in Chriſt and Chriſt believed in. We are not juſtifyed by our believing in Chriſt, but by our Chriſt believed in; even as we are not clothed by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the garments but by the garments put on; nor cured by applying the plaiſter, but by the plaiſter applyed Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is not only the object of that act which is imputed to us for righteouſneſs but it is the very thing the formal cauſe, the <hi>formalis ratio</hi> that makes us righteous in point of juſtification.</p>
            <p>To ſay that only the merit of Chriſts righteouſneſs, not the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs it ſelf is imputed to us, even as the demerit of <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, not his ſin are both ſpoken <hi>gratis;</hi> they tend to prove that Chriſt merited that faith might be accepted; which is ſuch another ſhift as that of the Papiſts Chriſt merited that we might merit; and therefore there is ſubtlety enough in ſo ſaying, but no truth in it For unleſs the ſin of <hi>Apam,</hi> and the righteoufnes of Chriſt be imputed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57355:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> the demerit or merit cannot; one being the foundation of the other, and inſeparable. Beſide, 'tis contrary to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 19. <hi>As by one mans diſobedience many were made ſinners ſo by the obedience of one, many righteous.</hi> We are ſinners by <hi>Adams</hi> diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, not by the demerit of it only; his very act of diſobedience is imputed to us, not only the demerit of it; and ſo for Chriſts obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: and it ſtands with reaſon, for <hi>Adam</hi> bare the perſon of all mankinde and therefore his act was ours, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 12. <hi>In whom all have ſinned,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, ſpeaking of <hi>Adam:</hi> Our Tranſlation renders it <hi>foraſmuch,</hi> but in the Original it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>In whom all have ſinned.</hi> As a father ſelling or forſeiting his eſtate, his act is the act of all his poſterity: ſo it is in this caſe, the very diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of <hi>Adam</hi> is imputed to us as our ſin not only the demerit of it; and likewiſe the very obedience of Chriſt is imputed to us for our righteouſneſs, not only the merit of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 6, 11. in both verſes a righteouſneſs is ſaid to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted; now there is no righteouſneſs any where to be found, but the righteouſneſs of Chriſt; Beſide, 'tis ſaid a righteouſneſs <hi>is impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;</hi> now imputation properly is, when ſomething that is in another perſon, is reckoned and accounted ours ſet upon our ſcore, our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, though indeed not in us, but in another perſon. That this is the ſignification of the word, appears from that of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, v.</hi> 18. <hi>If Oneſimus ow thee any thing, put that to my account,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſame word which before and elſewhere is uſed and tranſlated <hi>impute;</hi> and ſo both <hi>Reza</hi> and the old tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion render this Text; <hi>if Oneſimus owe thee any thing, illud mihi imputato;</hi> impute it to me, or ſet it upon my account, as we read it. Thus the righteouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed to us ſet upon our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, reckoned upon our ſcore, though not a thing in us of our own.</p>
            <p>If thus it be then let us in point of juſtification, give unto Chriſt<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pl.</hi> 1.</note> the things that are Chriſts, and unto faith, the things that are faiths. 'Tis honour enough for faith, that it is the grace whereby on our part we have union to Chriſt, and intereſt in the righteouſneſs of Chriſt; but to make faith it ſelf our righteouſneſs is to attribute more to it then it can bear, or will own. Set all due honour upon the head of faith, but do not break the back of it, by laying the whole weight of juſtification upon it; faith is too weak to bear it: God hath laid help upon one who is mighty, even the Lord our Righteoufneſs. And herein appears the free grace of God in point of our juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57355:12"/> that he was pleaſed to provide Jeſus Chriſt, and to accept of his righteouſneſs in our ſtead, that we believing in him, ſhould have his righteouſneſs imputed, and ſet upon our account. Chriſt is ſaid to have fulfilled all righteouſneſs and all the righteouſneſs he ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, is imputed to us, both active and paſſive doing and dying. Not that his paſſive redeem'd us from guilt and hell and that his active made us righteous and gave us title to heaven; but both of them joyntly concurr'd to effect each: both of them laid together, make up that price which Chriſt paid, that ſatisfaction which Chriſt made. Though the law doth not require both obeying and ſuffering. yet Chriſt paying not the <hi>idem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> but the <hi>tartundem,</hi> not the ſtrict debt it ſelf, but a valuable ſatisfaction, he might and did put the merit of his obeying to his ſuffering; that ſo there might be <hi>copioſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptio,</hi> and that he might ſave to the utmoſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> altogether, and all manner of waies. 'Tis a material enquiry, whether Chriſts interceſſion do not come in upon the like account? I only hint it.</p>
            <p>This is infinite matter of comfort to Saints that the righteouſnes<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Appl.</hi> 2.</note> of Chriſt, who fulfill'd all righteouſneſs, is imputed to them; for, hereby they ſtand as righteous in the ſight of God, as the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt can make them; yea, as righteous (in ſome ſenſe) as Chriſt himſelf; righteous with the ſame righteouſneſs, though not righteous in the ſame manner; He with his own inherent, we with his imputed; truly ours, though not in us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And this may be one ſenſe of that (if it be underſtood of Chriſt in: <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 17. <hi>Therefore have we boidneſs in the day of judgement, becauſe as he is, ſo are we</hi> &amp;c. If in point of ſanctification, much more in juſtification. We are juſt, not only for, but with the righteouſneſs of Chriſt that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs which will befit only the perſon of a Mediator. God-man, by way of inherency, may yet befit a creature by way of imputation. Nor does the imputation of ſuch a righteouſneſs, evacuate the duty of repentance: The righteous need no repentance; the moſt which can be forc'd from thence is only, that the inherently righteous need no repentance, but they who are only righteous by imputed righteouſneſs do. Touching the beſt of Saints, though a moſt perfect righteouſneſs be imputed to them, yet ſin is inherent in them, and therefore repentance needful for them.</p>
            <p>4. I come to the fourth link in the chain of our ſalvation which is regeneration; whereby we mean Gods making us new creatures, or his quickning us with ſpiritual life. And this the Apoſtlein <hi>Eſh.</hi> 2.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57355:13"/> attributes to Free Grace: Having told us <hi>v. 1. that of our ſelves we are dead in ſins,</hi> he explains in the next verſes what he means by it; not only dead in perſon, becauſe of the guilt of ſin; but dead in Nature, becauſe under the power of ſin. He does not ſay, dead for ſins, but dead in ſins; which implies the former, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes more: and then in <hi>v.</hi> 5. he attributes our quickning, unto grace: <hi>When we were dead in ſins, he quickned us; By grace ye are ſaved.</hi> This quickning of us, the Scripture calls Regeneration. <hi>A man muſt be born again, Joh. 3. 3. and that not of blood, nor of the will of the fleſh, nor of the will of man, but of God; Joh.</hi> 1. 13 or <hi>born of the Spirit, Joh.</hi> 3. 8. Theſe Texts compared, ſhew what is the adaequate principle of Regeneration, whether man's will, or Gods ſpirit, and tells us expreſly, <hi>totidem verbis, not the will of man, but the ſpirit of God.</hi> Imagine Regeneration to be divided into a 1000 degrees, yet we muſt not attribute ſo much as one of them to mans will, but all to Gods ſpirit: For the Scripture puts a flat oppoſition betwixt them in this point; <hi>born not of the will of man, but born of God, or born of the Spirit.</hi> As in the firſt birth we do not form our ſelves in the womb, but God, as the God of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture does all: So in this ſecond birth, we do not form the new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creature in our own hearts, but God as the God of grace does all. 'Tis true indeed, when once the will of man is principled and acted by the ſpirit of God, it acts with the ſpirit; <hi>Voluntas acta agit;</hi> and in this ſenſe we need not refuſe that former reſemblance, allowing only one part of a thouſand to the will of man, and the other nine hundred ninety nine to the ſpirit of grace in every ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual act. But this is after Regeneration, and therefore comes not home to the caſe in hand; <hi>Voluntas acta agit, ſed non agit niſi acta;</hi> after regeneration the will acts with and in the ſtrength of the Spirit; but in the firſt moment of converſion, as to the work of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, the Will ſtirs not it ſelf, but lies dead; and like the Chaos in the firſt Creation, moves not till the ſpirit of God move upon it. We are by Nature dead in every faculty, till the Lord quicken us, not only by the Spirits energetical preſence, but by the Spirits working a new principle in us; call it by what logical term you think fitteſt, whether habit or power, it is ſuch a principle as the Scripture calls Grace; 1 <hi>Cor. 15. 10. By the grace of God I am what I am; and his grace which was beſtowed upon me, was not in vain; but I laboured more abundantly then they all; yet not I,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57355:13"/> but the grace of God which was with me.</hi> By grace here, is not meant only the favour or grace of God towards <hi>Paul,</hi> but the grace of God in <hi>Paul;</hi> for he ſpeaks of it as a principle of action within him, ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling him for what he did: <hi>I laboured; yet not I, but the grace of God.</hi> And ſo <hi>Heb, 13. 9. It is a good thing that the heart be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with grace:</hi> beſide grace towards the perſon, there is grace in the heart, whereby the heart is ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to be eſtabliſhed, or poyſed and made ſteady. In both theſe places (to name no more) by grace is meant a principle put into us.</p>
            <p>There is another pregnant phraſe, which clearly imports, that when God regenerates us, he puts ſuch a principle into us; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 23. We are ſaid to be <hi>born again of incorruptible ſeed, by the word of God, which liveth and abideth for ever.</hi> In our regeneration there is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible ſeed put into us, of which the new creature is bred and born within us; which ſeed is not * the word of God; for we are ſaid to<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempt. Red, p. 199.</note> be born of the ſeed by the word: But by the ſeed is meant, a divine principle, wrought by God in the heart and ſoul, through the miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the word, which liveth and abideth for ever; <hi>i. e.</hi> not which word, but which ſeed or principle liveth and abideth in us for ever; as appears by the placing of the comma's, and as the word <hi>incorruptible</hi> imports. That this is no forced interpretation, but the proper meaning, will appear from a parallel Text, 1 <hi>Joh. 3. 9. Whoſoever is born of God, his ſeed remaineth in him.</hi> By ſeed is confeſſedly underſtood a divine principle wrought in us; and it is this ſeed that remaineth, ſaith this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Text; but how long remains it? That the former Text ſpeaks home to; not only for a ſeaſon, as ſome would interpret it, * but <hi>it liveth and</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> Ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</note> 
               <hi>abideth for ever.</hi> This is a ſtrong argument for perſeverance, which ſome endeavouring to anſwer, have only knock'd one part of the Text againſt another, and left the main thing againſt them untouched.</p>
            <p>But to return, till we be thus regenerated and quickned we are of our ſelves dead in every faculty; not only in our wills and affections but even in our underſtandings as to things of ſpiritual concernment. The Intellectual frame of the ſoul of man, was by the ſin and fall of <hi>Adam</hi> wholly diſſolv'd and ſhatter'd and brought into as great a confuſion of ignorance and darkneſs as can be imagined.</p>
            <p>Now if ſo, from hence I infer theſe two concluſions.</p>
            <p>1. Every man continues in this ſtate, till he be made a new creature by regeneration<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God by Chriſt hath not ſo heal'd this natural con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of mankind, that every one (even before generation) is reinveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57355:14"/> with ability to apprehend, diſcern, and ſubſcribe to the things of God. Chriſt hath not purchaſed any ſuch general vouchſafement to all the children of men, nor is any ſuch grace given to the world in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral upon the account of Chriſt, as is preſumed, not yet proved<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary appears; for till we be regenerate there is nothing in us but the old man; and that old man is in the old ſtate of darkneſs fore-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: there muſt be a renewing the ſpirit of our minds; now they only are renewed in the ſpirit of their minds, who have put on the new man <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 23, 24. it is the new man, who is renewed in knowledge, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 10. As touching that Text, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 9. where Chriſt is ſaid to be that <hi>light which lighteth every man coming into the world;</hi> there is differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence twixt lighting and enlightning; one reſpecting the object and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium, the other reſpecting the faculty: if that Scripture prove that Chriſt lighteth all <hi>i. e.</hi> holds forth in the Goſpel ſufficient outward light to ſee by yet it proves not that he inwardly enlightens all with a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple to ſee with. The Sun is the light of the material world, yet they upon whom Nature hath not beſtowed ſight, cannot ſee for all that. The Sun ſends out its light into the world far and near, yet the man who is born blinde, abides in darkneſs till his eyes be opened. <hi>I am come a light into the world,</hi> ſays Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12. 46. yet it is implyed in the next words, that every unbeliever abides in darkneſs; now we are all unbelievers till regenerate, and therefore till then abide in darkneſs, though under the very Tropicks of Goſpel light, yet we diſcern it not, till God give us an ey of faith, <hi>i. e.</hi> till he do that for us which the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calls <hi>enlightning the eyes of our underſtanding, Eph.</hi> 1. 18. till then, though the light ſhine, yet it ſhines in darkneſs, and the darkneſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends it not.</p>
            <p>Some by darkneſs in this and all other like texts, will needs under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Re. Re.</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face P 14. p. 20.</note> not a natural but only a contracted blindneſs; not born with us,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> in preface p. 12,</note> but which ſome (or it may be the moſt wilfully bring upon themſelves. And therefore I add,</p>
            <p>2. Not only ſuch unregenerate perſons, who have darkned their own minds, by looſe and ſenſual converſe and converſation, prepoſſeſſing themſelves with erroneous apprehenſions, but even the choyſeſt of the unregenerate, thoſe who are in their pureſt naturals, they are in darknes, as to the ſaying apprehenſion of ſpiritual things: for till they be born again or quickned they are dead, which deadneſs being univerſal, runs thorow every faculty, and imports not only a lameneſs, but an utter ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility in the underſtanding, as well as other faculties. The mouth of that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57355:14"/> Text is not yet ſtopt, 1 <hi>Cor. 2. 14. The natural man is not capable of the things of God, nor can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned;</hi> the original word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſouly man, <hi>i. e.</hi> the man who hath no other principles but thoſe connatural to his ſoul, no principles ſuper-infuſed from the ſpirit: ſuch a ſouly man cannot underſtand the things of the ſpirit of God, becauſe being things of the ſpirit, they are only ſpiritually diſcerned, <hi>i. e.</hi> by the Spirit which he that is only a ſouly man wants, I ſhall offer 3. things towards further clearing this Text.</p>
            <p>1. By the Natural man here, is not meant * the weak Chriſtian<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> in preface p. 13.</note> the babe in Chriſt, ſpoken of in the next chapter; for 'tis ſaid, <hi>the things of God are fooliſhnes to him;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which comes of the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to rebel.</hi> Now the things of God are not fooliſhnes to a weak Chriſtian, much leſs does his heart rebel againſt them; as the word ſeems to import: beſides the very word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> does properly ſignifie <hi>a man without the ſpirit,</hi> ſo S. <hi>Jude</hi> defines ſin, <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> our tranſlation renders it ſenſual, but 'tis the ſame word with this in the text; natural, having not the ſpirit. We find the ſame uſed again <hi>James 3. 15. this wiſdom is earthly, natural, diveliſh;</hi> in both theſe places the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpeaks an unregenerate condition; and I cannot meet the word again in all the new teſtament, ſave only in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15, where the Apoſtle diſtinguiſhes twixt natural and glorifyed bodies.</p>
            <p>2. It does not at all appear, that by the things of God here ſpoken of, are meant only high and deep myſteries, ſpeculations, but rather the ſubſtantial doctrines of the Goſpel, which the Apoſtle calls, <hi>the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Jeſus Chriſt, and him crucifyed; ver. 2. the things given to us of God, ver. 12. which are hidden and deep in reſpect of thoſe, who have only the ſpirit of the world and worldly wiſdom, ver.</hi> 6. 8. but (ſays <hi>Paul) we have received the ſpirit of God, that we might know them, and we alſo ſpeak them; compareing one ſpiritual thing with another, though the natural man is not capable of them, as having not the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. By the incapacity here mentioned, is not underſtood only a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent actuall incapacity, through want of diligent uſe of means; but an utter incapacity, through want of a principle, ſpiritual things are not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd but ſpiritually. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>vi ſolius ſpiritus, non vi.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: as <hi>Beza</hi> expounds it: the ſpirit is requiſite to the diſcerning of ſpiritual things, and therefore the natural man having not the ſpirit as <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks) wants that very principle whereby he ſhould diſcerne them.</p>
            <p>1. Let grace have its due acknowledgment, by attributing that to<note place="margin">
                  <hi>App.</hi> 1.</note>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:57355:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> it which the ſcripture termes making us to differ, <hi>who maketh thee to differ?</hi> ſays <hi>Paul, 1 Cor.</hi> 4. 7. Let the anſwer be, <hi>not I, but the grace of God which is in me; by the grace of God I am what I am.</hi> Let this be fully granted with the clear conſequences therof &amp; we deſire no more.</p>
            <p>But to ſay that * grace is the reſtauration or healing of the natural condition of<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face p. 14, 20.</note> man in general, through Chriſt; as if every man was born ſound and able, till he corrupt himſelf afterward, with the luſts of the fleſh, and ways of the world, this does not make grace to difference one man from another. Not is it enough to ſay, that not one of a thouſand but does ſo corrupt himſelf, that without a ſecond re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief from the grace of God, he never comes to believe: for this ſeems to imply a power, though rarely or never exerted into act. Whereas there is not one man in the world, îf it were poſſible for him nor ſo to corrupt himſelf, that hath ſo much as power to believe, without regenerating grace Which grace is not a reſtauration of the natural condition of men through Chriſt, whereby they are heal'd, till they cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt themſelves. Neither is it a ſecond relief anſwerable to, and removing ſuch a ſelf corruption; neither is it a put ing men into a capacity of believing, by vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafeing outward means, or holding ſo than object to be believed in; which ſome perhaps may term a power to believe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſubtilly, though improperly; neither is it only an irreſiſtable acting upon he underſtanding, by way of illumination; neither laſtly, will all theſe laid together, with an actual aſſiſtance in order to believing, come up to that which is indeed, and in truth, diſcriminating and diſterencing grace.</p>
            <p>Differencing grace is an incorruptible ſeed, put into ſome, not others; whereby they are made new Creatures, a divine ſpiritual principle, running thorow every faculty, by which they are inabled, and without which they were unable to put forth ſpiritual acts of ſaving import, ti true indeed, it is not God, or the grace of God, but man who believe, &amp; who is the ſubject of ſuch ſpiritual acts, having his own natural faculties ingaged in them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but yet man does not put forth thoſe ſpiritual act, by his own natural faculties, natural, but as ſpiritually inabled by this ſupervenient principle of grace.</p>
            <p>And upon this accompt, we are norto attribute the differencing of us to any-thing of our ſelves, but to this free grace of God: it was one part of God's great deſigne, to carry on the work of ſalvation in ſuch a way, that the creature might have no ground to glory in himſelf: but all the wit of man cannot avoid it, but that we may glory in our ſelves, if there be not ſuch a peculiar differencing grace.</p>
            <p>Take heed of crying down the doctrine of peculiar free graee as harſh; for to the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Appl.</hi> 2.</note> people of God none more ſweet. No doctrine does more indear Chriſt to the ſoul, and ingage the ſoul to Chriſt, then this of free grace, in all the branches of it. Acts of common love or civility amongſt men, doe nor lay ſuch a great obligation, as acts of peculiar love; when we pitch favours upon particular perſons theſe have alwaies the deepeſt impreſtion, &amp; came the heart yeſt returns. That the lot of free grace electing ſhould fall upon me (I mean it only by way of alluſion, let none take advan that expreſſion) that Chriſt ſhould love me, and give himſelf for me, that the ſpirit of God ſhould call, and cull our me, an I quicken me (ſays a Saint) this meits the heart Upon ſuch a conſideratio <hi>Paul</hi> hows his knee to the maſter of the families of heaven and earth, <hi>Eph.</hi> 9 14 and at <hi>v</hi> 18. prays, <hi>that the ſaints may be able</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to overtake the love of God in it, i. e.</hi> in ſome meaſure to wake up to it, and go along with it with a love anſwerable to it. Oh that thoſe who are ſo ready to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the defence of mans free will, would rather endeavour in the Apoſtles ſenſe, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the love of God towards them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57355:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
